Finding Aid for Provost and Executive Vice-President for Academic Affairs (University of Michigan) Central Files
Bentley Historical Library
Provost and Executive Vice-President for Academic Affairs (University of Michigan) Central Files
1961-2013
Bentley Historical Library
University of Michigan. Provost and Executive Vice-President for Academic Affairs.
87365 Bimu B6 2 [1]
1 oversize folder
605 linear feet (in 610 boxes)
50.6 GB (online)
Digital files
Central academic administrative unit of the University of Michigan which functions as chief executive assistant to the president, responsible for appointments and promotions with oversight for schools, colleges, educational units and programs; including budget planning, legislative relations, institutional research, and affirmative action policies. Central Files subgroup includes correspondence files of vice-presidents, associate and assistant vice-presidents, and other staff members within the vice-president's office.
The Provost's Office (Donor No. 5120 ) makes periodic additions to the records. Records were first received in 1971.
The VPAA Central Files are open for research except for certain records restricted by statute or university policy. Restricted material includes personnel-related files, including search, review, promotion, and tenure files; student educational records; client/patient records; and records of executive officers of the university.
The VPAA Central Files record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Personnel Related Records -- Boxes 295-319, 504-508, 575-581, 583-586, 599-601
Student Academic Records -- Boxes 295-319, 504-508, 575-581, 599
Patient/Client Records -- Boxes 309, 311-312, 314, 317-318, 504-508, 575-581, 601
Executive Officer Records -- Boxes 368-599, 602-610
Access to parts of the VPAA record group is restricted based on applicable law and university policy. Restricted material includes personnel files, search files, tenure and review files, grievance and disciplinary files and student files. In addition, the VPAA records are subject to these restrictions
Files of a vice president, or a member of his/her staff, still in office, are restricted.
Files of a vice president or a member of his/her staff, no longer in office, are restricted for ten years from the date of their origin. Files over ten years old are open. This restriction applies to files added to the record group prior to January 1, 2000.
Files added to the record group after January 1, 2000 are restricted for twenty years from the date they were added to the record group, in accord with the access policy for executive officer level records as described below. The VPAA record group does not, as yet, include any records in this category.
Access Restrictions for University of Michigan Records
University records are public records and once fully processed are generally open to research use. Records that contain personally identifiable information will be restricted in order to protect individual privacy. Certain administrative records are restricted in accordance with university policy as outlined below. The restriction of university records is subject to compliance with applicable laws, including the Michigan Freedom of Information Act.
Categories of Restricted Records
Personnel-related files, including search, review, promotion, and tenure files, are restricted for thirty (30) years from the date of their creation.
Student educational records: FERPA's protection of personally identifiable information in a student's education records ends at the time of a student's death and therefore is a matter of institutional policy. As a courtesy to the families of recently deceased students who were enrolled at the time of death, the University generally will not release information from their education records for five years without the consent of the deceased student's next of kin. Eighty-five (85) years after the date the records were first created, the University will presume that the student is deceased. Thereafter the student's education records will be open. Student records at the Bentley Historical Library are restricted for eighty-five (85) years, but may also be made available upon proof of the death of the student.
Patient/client records are restricted for one-hundred (100) years from the date of their creation. The terms of use for particular records older than 100 years may require the research to sign a Patient/Client Access Agreement.
Executive records: Records generated by the university's executive officers, deans, directors, department heads, and their designated support staff are restricted for twenty (20) years from the date of their creation.
Restricted files are indicated in the contents list of the collection’s finding aid with a restriction note indicating the restriction type and the date of expiration.
For further information on the restriction policy and placing Freedom of Information Act requests for restricted material, consult the reference archivist at the Bentley Historical Library (bentley.ref@umich.edu) or the University of Michigan Freedom of Information Office website (https://foia.vpcomm.umich.edu/).
As of 1995 the office represented by this record group is officially titled the Office of the Provost and Executive Vice President for Academic Affairs. Previous titles of the office were: Vice Presidents for Academic Affairs and Provost, 1983-1995; Vice President for Academic Affairs, 1962-1983; and Provost, 1938-1962.
Provost
The origins of this office date back to 1938, during President Ruthven's administration, when the position of provost was created by a bylaw of the Board of Regents to "aid the President by performing such of the President's functions as shall from time to time be delegated by him or by the Board of Regents" (Regents' Proceedings, March 1938, p. 505). E. Blythe Stason, the dean of the Law School who had already been performing many of these functions, was appointed the first provost. Stason resigned as provost in November 1944 to devote his attentions to the leadership of the Law School, and James P. Adams, vice president of Brown University and former University of Michigan economics professor, assumed the post of provost and professor of economics in January 1945. At the Regents' meeting of January 1945 the bylaw establishing the provost's position was amended to include the statement that the provost "shall be the chief executive officer of the University next to the President" (Regents' Bylaw 2.02). Adams remained the provost until his resignation in July 1951. A successor to Adams was not named, and the responsibilities of the provost were absorbed by the newly created vice president and dean of faculties, Marvin Niehuss.
Vice President for Academic Affairs
In 1962 two new positions were created in the university administration: executive vice president and vice president for academic affairs.
Marvin Niehuss, vice president for university relations since 1945 and the vice president and dean of faculties since 1951, was promoted to the position of executive vice president in 1962. As vice president and dean of faculties, Niehuss had coordinated university relations with the state legislature and had overseen the administration of the schools, colleges, and other units (including institutes, Extension Service, summer session, and the Reserve Officers' Training Corps), reporting on enrollment, teaching loads, research, and faculty salaries. In his new position as executive vice president, Niehuss continued to supervise legislative relations and served as the University's contact with the state board of education. In addition, the executive vice president was the chief executive assistant to the president and assumed the duties and powers of the president in his absence. (When Niehuss retired in 1968 the position of executive vice president was abolished and a vice president for state relations and planning was established in its place.)
Roger Heyns, a member of the Psychology Department and since 1959 dean of the College of Literature, Science and the Arts, was appointed to the position of vice president for academic affairs in 1962. Heyns assumed many of the duties previously performed by the vice president and dean of faculties. He was given general executive responsibility for the faculty and for the academic programs of the schools, colleges, and other educational units. He reviewed recommendations of deans, directors, and department heads with regard to appointments, promotions, leaves of absence, and salaries of faculty members and special service personnel. In addition, the Offices of Admissions, and Registration and Records--previously under the jurisdiction of the vice president for student affairs--were brought under the vice president for academic affairs.
This reorganization of administrative responsibilities was intended as a means of unifying planning in a period of rapid growth of the University. In actual practice, the duties associated with planning remained dispersed and were shifted from one office to another in the 1960s and 1970s. When a vice presidency for state relations and planning was established in 1968, some of the responsibility for academic program planning was transferred to that office. The Office of Institutional Research, which collected and analyzed data on enrollment trends, faculty characteristics, funding, and related subjects, was transferred in 1969 from Academic Affairs to State Relations and Planning. In 1974 the Office of Institutional Research was renamed the Office of Academic Planning and Analysis and was returned to Academic Affairs, reflecting the assignment of additional evaluation and planning responsibilities under the vice president for academic affairs. Over the course of the 1960s and 1970s, the vice president for academic affairs gradually assumed greater responsibility for budget preparation.
In addition to program and budget planning, the Office of Academic Affairs was involved in implementing affirmative action plans, overseeing the Opportunity Program and Tuskegee-Michigan exchange program, and coordinating support services for minority students.
When Roger Heyns left the university in 1965 to become chancellor of the University of California at Berkeley, he was succeeded by Allan F. Smith, the dean of the Law School. Smith held the post of vice president for academic affairs for nine years and in 1974 was followed by Frank H. T. Rhodes, a professor of geology and since 1971 dean of the College of Literature, Science, and the Arts. Rhodes resigned in 1977 to assume the presidency of Cornell University.
Harold T. Shapiro, chairman of the Economics Department, was appointed vice president for academic affairs in 1977 and held the position until 1980, when he became president of the University of Michigan. Alfred Sussman, dean of Rackham School of Graduate Studies, served as acting vice president for academic affairs from November 1, l979 through July 1, l980, when Billy E. Frye, professor of Zoology and dean of the College of Literature, Science, and the Arts, assumed the position.
Vice President for Academic Affairs and Provost
At its February 1983 meeting, the Regents of the University of Michigan changed the title of the position to Vice President for Academic Affairs and Provost (hereafter referred to as "provost"). The move to include "provost" in the title was taken in part because of the increased responsibility of the vice president within the university's administration and because of the need to assist the president as he moved into state and national projects, notably the management of the capital campaign fund-raising effort.
In 1986, Billy E. Frye resigned and was replaced by James J. Duderstadt, dean of the College of Engineering, who served as provost until he became the president of the university in September 1988. Robert Holbrook served as interim provost until December 1988. In January 1989, Charles Vest, dean of the College of Engineering, became provost and remained until July 1990, when he left to assume the presidency of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Holbrook served as interim provost for the month of August, after which Gilbert Whitaker, dean of the School of Business Administration, began his tenure as provost.
Provost and Executive Vice President for Academic Affairs
In September 1993 the Regents approved a change in title to provost and executive vice president for academic affairs. This title was intended to reflect more accurately the responsibilities of the provost and to "bring Michigan into line with the administrative structures of other universities" (The University Record 49(3), 1993 September 20: 4). The new designation came about when President Duderstadt recommended a change in title for Whitaker. In 1995 Whitaker returned to teaching and was succeeded by J. Bernard Machen, dean of the School of Dentistry. Machen initially served on an interim basis before agreeing to accept a two-year appointment. He did not seek an extension and was succeeded by Nancy Cantor, dean of the Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies in 1997.
The position vice provost for academic affairs was created in 1990 to recognize university-wide activities in which John H. D'Arms, dean of Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies, was engaged that were beyond the scope of his decanal responsibilities. Such responsibilities included overseeing the Bentley Historical Library and the Clements Library, evaluating promotion and tenure dossiers, and serving as liaison between the university and major foundations (The University Record 45(24), 1990 March 26: 1). With the appointment of new provosts the functional responsibilities and reporting relationships of the vice provost have frequently changed.
Provost and Executive Vice President for Academic Affairs
1993-1995 Gilbert R. Whitaker, Jr.
1996 J. Bernard Machen (interim)
1996-1997 J. Bernard Machen
1997-2001 Nancy Cantor
2001 Lisa Tedesco (interim)
2002 Paul N. Courant (interim)
2002-2005 Paul N. Courant
2005-2006 Edward M. Gramlich (interim)
2006-2010 Teresa A. Sullivan
2010-2013 Philip J. Hanlon
2013-2017 Martha E. Pollack
2017- Martin A. Philbert
Vice Presidents for Academic Affairs and Provost
1962-1965 Roger W. Heyns
1965-1974 Allen F. Smith
1974-1977 Frank H.T. Rhodes
1977-1979 Harold T. Shapiro
1979-1980 Alfred S. Sussman (Interim)
1980-1986 Billy E. Frye
1986-1988 James J. Duderstadt
1988 Robert S. Holbrook (Interim)
1989-1990 Charles M. Vest
1990 Robert S. Holbrook (Interim)
1990-1993 Gilbert R. Whitaker, Jr.
Vice Provost for Academic Affairs
1990-1995 John H. D'Arms
Vice Provosts for Academic Affairs – Graduate Studies
1995-1997 Nancy Cantor
1998-2004 Earl Lewis
2004 Steven L. Kunkel (interim)
2005- Janet Weiss
Senior Vice Provosts
2001- Lester Monts
Vice Provosts for Academic and Faculty Affairs
2007- Lori J. Pierce
2009-2014 Christina L. B. Whitman
2014 Sara B. Blair
Vice Provosts for Academic and Budgetary Affairs
2007-2010 Philip J. Hanlon
2010-2013 Martha E. Pollack
2013-2016 Alfred Franzblau
2016- Amy Dittmar
Associate Provosts
1993-1997 Robert Holbrook
1993-1997 Susan Lipschutz
1997-2002 Pamela A. Raymond
1997-2001 Lester P. Monts
1998-2002 Paul N. Courant
2001-2005 James L. Hilton
2002-2005 Valerie P. Castle
2002-2005 Janet Weiss
2004-2007 Philip J. Hanlon
2005-2007 Lori J. Pierce
Associate Vice Presidents
1971-1975 John Romani
1974-1981 Richard English
1975-1981 Carolyne K. Davis
1981-1993 Robert S. Holbrook
1981-1983 W. Allen Spivey
1983-1993 Mary Ann Swain
1984-1986 Niara Sudarkasa
1988-1989 John H. Jackson
Administrative Deans
1962-1974 Robert L. Williams
Assistant Vice Presidents
1974/75-1982 Edward A. Dougherty
1965-1982 Ernest R. Zimmermann
1983-1995 Robert B. Holmes
Associate Vice President
2002 Marilyn G.Knepp
Assistant Provost
1997-2000 Marilyn G. Knepp
1999-2008 Linda H. Gillum
1999-2002 K. B. Soper
2002-2011 Glenda Haskell
2011- Philip R. Hughes
Associate Vice Provost
2002 Glenna Schweitzer
Chief of Staff
1998-2013 Karen L. Gibbons
2013- Stephanie Riegle
2014- Erin Fluharty
The records of the VPAA are divided into in three subroups: Central Files, Supplemental Files and Staff Files. Each of the subsseries is described in separate finding aid. The Central files are further organized into series by fiscal year and each year may include an Alphabetical File, Schools and Colleges file and a Chronological file.
Summary Contents List - Central Files
1961/1962
Alphabetical Files -- Box 1
1962/1963
Alphabetical Files -- Box 1
1963/1964
Alphabetical Files -- Box 1
1964/1965
Alphabetical Files -- Boxes 1-2
1965/1966
Alphabetical Files -- Box 2
1966/1967
Alphabetical Files -- Boxes 2-7
1967/1968
Alphabetical Files -- Boxes 7-12
1968/1969
Alphabetical Files -- Boxes 13-19
1969/1970
Alphabetical Files -- Boxes 20-28
1970/1971
Alphabetical Files -- Boxes 28-29
1971/1972
Alphabetical Files -- Boxes 29-38
1972/1973
Alphabetical Files -- Boxes 38-47
1973/1974
Alphabetical Files -- Boxes 48-57
1974/1975
Alphabetical Files -- Boxes 57-65
Schools and Colleges Files -- Boxes 65-68
1975/1976
Alphabetical Files -- Boxes 68-75
Schools and Colleges Files -- Boxes 76-78
1976/1977
Alphabetical Files -- Boxes 79-84
Schools and Colleges Files -- Boxes 84-87
1977/1978
Alphabetical Files -- Boxes 88-95
Schools and Colleges Files -- Boxes 95-99
1978/1979
Alphabetical Files -- Boxes 99-107
Schools and Colleges Files -- Boxes 107-111
1979/1980
Alphabetical Files -- Boxes 111-116
Schools and Colleges Files -- Boxes 117-119
1980/1981
Alphabetical Files -- Boxes 119-125
Schools and Colleges Files -- Boxes 125-128
1981/1982
Alphabetical Files -- Boxes 129-136
Schools and Colleges Files -- Boxes 136-139
1982/1983
Alphabetical Files -- Boxes 139-147
Schools and Colleges Files -- Boxes 147-151
1983/1984
Alphabetical Files -- Boxes 151-163
Schools and Colleges Files -- Boxes 164-171
1984/1985
Alphabetical Files -- Boxes 172-185
Chronological Files -- Boxes 185-186
Schools and Colleges Files -- Boxes 186-192
1985/1986
Alphabetical Files -- Boxes 193-206
Chronological Files -- Boxes 206-207
Schools and Colleges Files -- Boxes 208-212
1986/1987
Alphabetical Files -- Boxes 213-228
Schools and Colleges Files -- Boxes 228-232
Chronological Files -- Boxes 233-236
1987/1988
Alphabetical Files -- Boxes 237-246
Schools and Colleges Files -- Boxes 246-248
Chronological Files -- Boxes 249-253
1988/1989
Alphabetical Files -- Boxes 254-261
Schools and Colleges Files -- Boxes 261-264
Chronological Files -- Boxes 265-267
1989/1990
Alphabetical Files -- Boxes 268-277
Schools and Colleges Files -- Boxes 278-281
Units Budget Files -- Boxes 281
Chronological Files -- Boxes 282
1990/1991
Alphabetical Files -- Boxes 283-290
Schools and Colleges Files -- Boxes 290-293
Chronological Files -- Boxes 293-294
1991/1992
Alphabetical Files -- Boxes 320-327
Schools and Colleges Files -- Box 328
Chronological Files -- Box 329
1992/1993
Alphabetical Files -- Boxes 330-335
Schools and Colleges Files -- Boxes 336-337
Chronological Files -- Box 329
1993/1994
Alphabetical Files -- Boxes 338-343
Schools and Colleges Files -- Boxes 344
Chronological Files -- Box 345
1994/1995
Alphabetical Files -- Boxes 347-353
Schools and Colleges Files -- Boxes 354-355
Chronological Files -- Box 356
1995/1996
Alphabetical Files -- Boxes 358-365
Schools and Colleges Files -- Boxes 365-367
Chronological Files -- Box 356-357
1996/1997
Alphabetical Files -- Boxes 368-375
Schools and Colleges Files -- Boxes 375-376
Chronological Files -- Box 357
1997/1998
Alphabetical Files -- Boxes 377-389
Schools and Colleges Files -- Boxes 390-393
1998/1999
Alphabetical Files -- Boxes 393-404
Schools and Colleges Files -- Boxes 404-407
Chronological Files -- Boxes 487
1999/2000
Alphabetical Files -- Boxes 407-419
Schools and Colleges Files -- Boxes 420-423
Chronological Files -- Boxes 487-488
2000/2001
Alphabetical Files -- Boxes 423-435
Schools and Colleges Files -- Boxes 435-438
Chronological Files -- Box 488-489
2001/2002
Alphabetical Files -- Boxes 438-450
Schools and Colleges Files -- Boxes 450-452
Chronological Files -- Boxes 489
2002/2003
Alphabetical Files -- Boxes 454-469
Schools and Colleges Files -- Boxes 469-472
Chronological Files -- Box 490
2003/2004
Alphabetical Files -- Boxes 472-483
Schools and Colleges Files -- Boxes 484-486
Chronological Files -- Boxes 490-491, 503
2004/2005
Alphabetical Files -- Boxes 491-501
Schools and Colleges Files -- Boxes 501-503
Chronological Files -- Boxes 583-584
2005/2006
Alphabetical Files -- Boxes 509-517, 575
Schools and Colleges Files -- Boxes 517-519, 575
Chronological Files -- Box 584
2006/2007
Alphabetical Files -- Boxes 519-529, 575-576
Schools and Colleges Files -- Boxes 529-531, 576
Chronological Files -- Box 585
2007/2008
Alphabetical Files -- Boxes 532-541, 576-577
Schools and Colleges Files -- Boxes 542-543, 578
Chronological Files -- 585-586
2008/2009
Alphabetical Files -- Boxes 543-554, 578
Schools and Colleges Files -- Boxes 554-556, 579
Chronological Files -- 586-587
2009/2010
Alphabetical Files -- Boxes 556-564, 579-580
Schools and Colleges Files -- Boxes 564-565, 580
Chronological Files -- 587, 599
2010/2011
Alphabetical Files -- Boxes 582 (oversize), 565-573, 580
Schools and Colleges Files -- Boxes 573-574, 581
Chronological Files -- Boxes 583-587, 599-600
2011/2012
Alphabetical Files -- Boxes 581, 587-596, 599
Schools and Colleges Files -- Boxes 596-599
Chronological Files -- Box 601
2012/2013
Alphabetical Files -- Boxes 601-608
Schools and Colleges Files -- Boxes 609-610
The records of the Provost and Executive Vice President for Academic Affairs date from 1947 to 1997 and total more than 675 linear feet. The records are a rich source of information on the University of Michigan from the 1960s to the present. They contain a wide variety of material documenting the concerns of the administration and, to a lesser extent, the faculty and students regarding academic programs, student and faculty activities, and the administrative operations of the University of Michigan.
The records, which include the provost's files as well as the files of associate and assistant vice presidents, are arranged in three subgroups: Central Files, Staff Files, and Supplemental Files. The Central Files subgroup consists of the records maintained by the provost's office and is discussed in greater detail below. The Staff Files subgroup includes the records of assistant and associate vice presidents and of the assistants to the provost. The Supplemental Files subgroup contains material on specific topics to which a number of academic affairs staff contributed their efforts, including retreats, unit reviews, and searches. Each of the subgroups is fully described in a separate finding aid.
It should be noted that some of the records in the record group predate the founding of the Office of Academic Affairs. Such records were generally brought by vice presidents or staff members from previous positions or inherited from persons who formerly performed their duties.
The Central Files subgroup consists of 605 linear feet dating from the creation of the Office of Academic Affairs in the academic year 1961/1962 to 2012/2013. The records consist primarily of correspondence, minutes and other committee files, reports, and budget materials, reflecting the broad range of responsibilities and functions of the provost. Whereas the records of the Staff Files subgroup tend to document the process of policy formation and decision-making functions, the Central Files records more often contain finished products, such as reports and policy statements. For the researcher interested in the provost's views on a particular topic or issue, or the Office of Academic Affairs involvement in the academic and financial life of various schools and colleges, the Central Files subgroup is the single best starting point.